Guide to the Milton R. Rackmil Memorabilia Collection MSS.073
Fales Library and Special Collections
Milton R. Rackmil Memorabilia Collection
1938-1990
1953-1972
Fales Library and Special Collections
Rackmil, Milton R., 1906-1992
MSS.073
5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, and 7 flat boxes
5 sound discs (vinyl)
Milton R. Rackmil (1906-1992) was a native New Yorker and a New York University graduate. In 1934, Rackmil founded Decca Records with Jack Kapp and Edward Lewis, and became president in 1949. Decca Records became the largest shareholder in the Universal Pictures Company in 1951, and in 1952 Rackmil took over as president. MCA bought Decca and Universal in 1962 and Rackmil became vice chairman of MCA's board. He remained head of MCA's film and record companies until his retirement in 1972. This collection documents Rackmil's career in the music and motion picture industries. Materials include scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, plaques, publicity, certificates, speeches, annual reports, correspondence, ephemera, and five vinyl records dating from 1938 to 1990. The bulk of the collection focuses on memorabilia from Rackmil's time at Decca Records and Universal Pictures from 1938-1972.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1994.073.
Appraisal
One piece of rolled ephemera was reviewed by the curator for deaccession. The ephemera consisted of a muscial score in which the song lyrics were written about Rackmil. The ephemera was laminated and rolled, and has significantly deteriorated over time. The item was deaccessioned due to the deterioration and low historic value.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in the order in which they were recieved from the donor.
Biographical Note
Milton R. Rackmil (1906-1992) was born in the Lower East Side of New York City. He grew up in Brooklyn and graduated from NYU with a degree in accounting. In 1934, Rackmil founded Decca Records with Jack Kapp and Edward Lewis, and became president in 1949. Decca Records became the largest shareholder in the Universal Pictures Company in 1951, and in 1952 Rackmil took over as president. MCA bought Decca and Universal in 1962 and Rackmil became vice chairman of MCA's board. He remained head of MCA's film and record companies until his retirement in 1972.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents Milton R. Rackmil's career in the music and motion picture industries from 1938 up to his retirement in 1972. Materials include scrapbooks documenting a 1953 European sales convention, trips around the world that Rackmil took with colleagues from Universal Pictures in 1953, the 1962 Motion Picture Pioneer of the Year Annual Dinner honoring Rackmil; and the 1965 New York Variety Club Celebrity Ball. Other memorabilia include photographs related to travel and banquets that include photos with colleagues and celebrities, including Sammy Davis Jr.; clippings, awards plaques, and publicity related to Rackmil's career in the music and motion picture industries, including Decca Records' 20th, 25th, and 30th anniversaries; certificates from various airlines for good fortune while traveling; and speeches Rackmil gave to the New York Stock Exchange in 1960 and at the 1962 Motion Picture Pioneer of the Year Annual Dinner where he accepted the Pioneer of the Year Award. This collection also includes a 1959 annual report for Decca Records; stock market reports for Decca Records; an invitation to meet the President of the United States over cocktails and dinner for the White House News Photographers' Association Dinner; a lifetime pass to the Country Music Hall of Fame and Museum; five audio recordings on vinyl records of banquets and various artists; and draft reports, correspondence, and a press release related to the 1952 acquisition of Decca Records by Universal Pictures and the 1990 acquisition of MCA by Matsushita Electrical Industrial Co.
Music industry; Motion picture industry; Rackmil, Milton R., 1906-1992; Decca Records (Firm); Universal Pictures (Firm)
- Vinyl record - Larry Evans and His Quartet, undated (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 1)
- Vinyl record - Murray Arnold, undated (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 2)
- Vinyl record - London Banquet in honour of the United States and Canadian distributors for the Decca Record Company Limited, 1964 (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 3)
- Vinyl record - Dinner given by Mr. and Mrs. Eric Gallo to celebrate the 25th anniversary of the entry of Mr. E.R. Lewis into the Gramophone Record Industry, 1956 (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 4-5)
- Photographs with colleagues, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Speech given at the New York Stock Exchange, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs re traveling and banquets, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Certificates from Japan Airlines and Qantas Empire Airlines, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- MCA Merger with Matsushita Electrical Industrial Co., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Personal publicity re Rackmil's career, 1957-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
- Photographs with Sammy Davis, Jr., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Clippings re Decca Records' 20th Anniversary, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Clippings re Decca Records' 25th Anniversary, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 30th Anniversary (permanent) Decca Records, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Decca Records annual report and invoice for a tin of caviar, 1959, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence re Decca Records, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Ephemera and photographs re Rackmil's career and acheivements, 1962-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Certificate for a dinner given in honor of Milton R. Rackmil, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Memorandum on allocation of defense materials to phonograph record industry, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Clippings re MCA and the 1965 Country Music Festival, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Draft report for the acquisition of assets of Decca Records by Universal Pictures, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual meeting of Decca Records, Inc., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and contracts re Decca Records and Universal Pictures, 1951-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Letter found in the Universal Pictures world tour with Alfred E. Daff scrapbook, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Milton Rackmil with wife Jackie (in Acapulco and N.Y.) found in the Universal Pictures world tour with Alfred E. Daff scrapbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Pioneer Dinner Speech found in the Motion Picture Pioneer of the Year Twenty Fourth Annual Dinner honoring Milton R. Rackmil scrabbook, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Pioneer Dinner photographs found in the Motion Picture Pioneer of the Year Twenty Fourth Annual Dinner honoring Milton R. Rackmil scrabbook, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Scrapbook - Around the World in 30 Days, 1953-09-11-1953-10-12 (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
- Personal Publicity re Rackmil's career, 1951-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Decca Records, Inc. securities and exchange reports, 1938-1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Personal Publicity, 1954-1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Clippings re motion picture industry, 1956-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Photograph of Universal - International Sales Executives Conference, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- National advertisements for Decca Records, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- City Paper, 1984 (Box Shared Fales 004, Folder 7)
- Commemorative pen holder, 1962 (Box 5, Object 1)
- Commemorative glass plaque, 1964 (Box 5, Object 2)
- Award plaque, 1955 (Box 5, Object 3)
- Scrapbook - Universal International European Conference, Barcelona, June 7-10, 1954 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook - European Sales Convention, Rome, Italy, June 1953 (Box 7)
- Scrapbook - Universal Pictures world tour with Alfred E. Daff, 1953 (Box 8)
- Scrapbook - Variety Club of New York Celebrity Ball, Friday, November 12, 1965 (Box 9)
- Scrapbook - Motion Picture Pioneer of the Year Twenty Fourth Annual Dinner honoring Milton R. Rackmil, November 19th, 1962 (Box 9)
- Scrapbook - Motion Picture Pioneer of the Year, 1962 (Box 10)